Okay. Few about a month ago, maybe a
couple of months ago, I was at Devox
Belgium and I met this guy called Alex
Gabillescu. Uh, was that British or was
that [laughter]
It was good. Okay, cool. Um, I've been
told my my pronunciation of the of of
Alex's surname is very British. Uh but
Alex Gabilelescu and Alex built this
awesome tool called Batlog MD. Um and
Alex will go through this but it's
really really amazing to see what can be
built with a very spec driven approach.
Um and well without further ado, Alex is
going to walk you through it. Please
welcome Alex on stage.
>> Hello everyone. Thank you. [applause]
Thank you for joining me here. So today
we're going to talk about backlog MD but
uh also we're going to have the workshop
session to use backlog MD MD u directly
in one of your tasks. Um so let's start
immediately.
So who am I? I'm Alex Gavlescu. I'm a
lead engineer in Vienna, Austria. Uh I
speak Romanian, Italian, English. uh
when you see me like uh afterwards you
can talk in any of these languages. Uh I
have 13 years of experience as a
developer using .NET, Kubernetes, cloud
all of these things. [snorts]
But recently I tried to enter the AI
world um and what better way to actually
learn things than uh building tools uh
yourself. So backlog MD was an idea that
I had uh for working to manage uh
working on my side projects. So I wanted
to structure a little bit my work and I
started working on it in June and
actually today uh we might get to 4,000
GitHub stars. Uh there are 3,990
something. So if you guys would like uh
re make me reach 4,000 uh GitHub stars
today, that would be cool. Uh but yeah,
so what are we going to talk today? Um
so first I'm going to give you some
context. If uh anyone of you uh went to
Lada's talk a bit earlier uh they they
would have to skip this context because
her her introduction to AI and all of
these things was is more than enough.
But for who uh doesn't work with AI
every day, uh I'm going to keep you uh
put you up to date.
Then uh I'm going to go through my
journey with AI and hopefully this
resonates with you and understand why I
came up with backlog.
Then we're going to talk about
specdriven AI development and why it's
important and some conclusions and then
we're going to have a break and we're
going to start with the workshop. In the
workshop uh I'm going to uh let you code
whatever you want and I'm going to come
uh to your desk and assist you.
So the context uh this is very important
not only for AI agents as you uh know
but also for humans. So the how do we
started few years ago with code
completions you would start typing
something in your ID and then with AI or
even without AI it will try to
autocomplete with functions from uh from
your code or try to like guess what you
want to do. This was like very early.
Then we had the chat GPT kind of
interactions where you would copy your
code, put it in chat GPT, ask fix my
code and then you will copy back the
solution hopefully working back into
your ID. And this was already like an
enhancement of this. But what's really
made it work much better is the ID
extension. So this really revolutionizes
how we work with AI because you would
have the AI agents directly in your code
basically in your ID sitting uh next to
your files and uh you could add any file
of your uh repository and then the agent
would know about it. So in the first
version you could only ask questions and
it evolved into um edit mode and
afterwards it evolved into agent mode
and agent actually evolved outside of
your ID and they became CLI agents. the
CLI agents are like for what I think
like the next step and what um what
feels to be the the the way that
developers really like to work with code
because um it allows developers to like
hand over tasks and let agents work for
like minutes, hours and in the future
maybe even days and then get back a
working uh result.
So
what are AI agents very quickly? So they
are a system that use AI models to
perform tasks autonomously and can
interact with other tools, the API
databases to achieve their goals.
So there are few ways to interact with
the AI agents. Uh Matt uh give a very
nice representation um of how how we're
working. So we have never looking at
code and just prompting all the time and
this is what we call vibe coding. Um you
don't get great results with this. Also
if you even if you are developer that
knows how to code and you check every
single line of code but you always like
try to get your way by just prompting uh
you might have like you will not get too
far. Then on the left side you have more
structured way of working. So you uh if
you worked on bigger projects uh either
in enterprise companies or like just
structure your work with uh scrum
frameworks where you have the whole
sprint planned ahead. uh you would
probably like to achieve the same uh
workflow with AI and you start with the
specs what you want to achieve and you
either are the developer that checks
every single line of code or you're a
project manager that just wants the
result somehow working and this is um
what I'm I'm going to talk more about
and my journey is basically this so I
started with like just prompting and
slowly I'm I'm going towards not even
looking too much at the code. I just
look at the outputs of the code uh and
and move to the next task.
So, how was my uh how was my story?
Probably like a lot of uh people uh
resonate with you. So, just prompting
like I said uh doesn't go too far. It
feels like a slot machine. And it feels
like sometimes it's good, sometimes it's
really bad and it's very random.
And with this I achieved around 50%
success rate which in my case it means
that I I managed successfully to u
implement the task without giving up
completely. So even if I have to go back
and forth a couple of times
um
>> I still consider it successfully.
So then I added agent instructions where
I would put all of my important
information
uh also about the testing how I want it
to be uh tested the linting and this way
I achieved around 75 success rate. It
was quite an improvement but it was not
amazing. And uh it led me like think
what can I do better to to fix this
problem and then I realized that
obviously like I realized myself but it
was very clear from the beginning that
AI models are not deterministic and I
just needed to make the process more
deterministic.
>> But I was chatting with him earlier
>> and um
>> yeah so how to make the flow more
deterministic. So uh for me what worked
very well is to split the the big
feature into smaller tasks and each of
them should fit in a in a context
window. Um how many of you like to use
compaction in with AI agency
>> you like to use compaction. Okay
>> you that that's a good that's a good
question. So you like to use compaction
or you have to use compaction. Uh when
you uh run out of context window, one of
the solutions that uh AI agents
implemented is compaction which means
basically take the whole conversation
until now and summarize it and obviously
it's going to uh take a bit of context
window but not hopefully the like the
whole context window and so you can
start coding again in the same session.
The problem with this is that you lose
important information because this
summary you cannot control what gets
carried over. Sometimes it's like just
stuff that should be thrown away and uh
for me like uh splitting the the feature
into smaller task was the solution.
And uh coming from my uh like agile
workflow
always mentioning the why, the what and
the how for each task.
And actually uh a very important step
was to ask AI sort of a feedback to to
ask
ask them to write what they understood
from my task from my request. So, hey, I
want to build this super fancy CLI tool
to store my all of my tasks as markdown.
Can you create a plan to to implement
this and AI would actually
>> write it down the way he understood it?
it understood it and I can verify
>> and this also comes from my uh work um
like uh professional work have a clear
definition of done what means that
something is finished and can be merged
into the and pushed to production.
>> So the solution for me was write uh the
tasks as markdown files
>> extremely
>> reuse the the same template. So I
basically copied a little bit my GR
workflow that I use at work. So a
description like why why are we doing
this task a bunch of acceptance criteria
that have to be done uh in a way that
you can actually test the acceptance
criteria
>> an implementation plan so that I usually
share with the team. Hey I would like to
implement this feature in this way uh
and I write it down
>> and some implementation notes that are
usually like the PR notes like I did it
this way for this reasons.
And uh saving those this information as
markdown files in git allows you to just
tell the agent hey work on this task
which is in this markdown file.
>> This makes the loop more predictable and
less nondeterministic.
So the agent could read the tasks
directly from the files and they have to
implement all of the acceptance
criterias and nothing else. There was a
point at the very beginning where Claude
was just going too far ahead and tried
to implement things that were uh not
requested. And with this I I really
mitigated the problems. He he would it
would have to implement only those
acceptance criteria and nothing else.
And the definition of done uh means that
the agent says like I am done when the
all of acceptance acceptance criteria
has are done and the test are um are
passing.
>> So this uh was a great success for me.
Uh this way I achieved around 95% of
task uh being merged without throwing
away the whole code. So it was nice also
from the financial uh perspective
because I I would not run out of tokens
uh with my plans.
>> So it was a good start but
>> there's numbers
>> there were some problems with this
approach. So
um if I asked AI, hey can you create a
task for implementing this feature like
I want to build backlog MD uh and then
it will create a markdown file but the
structure might not be the one that I
expect. It might not have acceptance
criteria. Sometimes I had the agent
completely hallucinating the the
structure of the tasks
and I'm not uh I would not be able to
know which task are completed and which
task are still to do. I would have to
manually handle this like when the task
is completed I would have to either move
it to completed task if I still want to
reference it in the future or I would
have to delete it manually.
And uh coming from J I would miss uh
important features like labels,
dependencies and some metadata when a
task is created uh priorities and so on.
So my solution was backlog MD. Uh this
is an image generated with Nano Banana
and it was um
uh it was like a trend few weeks ago to
ask Nano Banana to generate a image of
how your tool would look in 1995. And if
you think about backlog MD, so I will
tell you now, it's a CLI um tool to have
uh a comban board in your uh terminal.
This could actually have been
implemented in 1995. So I think this
image fits a lot. So what is uh backlog
MD? It's a terminal based project
management tool that's extremely
effective to keep your task structured
uh with the agents.
So first of all, it's a CLI tool. And
what does it mean? So uh I think I hope
everyone is familiar with at least this
uh CLI command. Um maybe some of you use
uh git UI uh tools, but probably
everyone had to to run this uh command
at least once. So with backlog MD, it's
very similar. You have CLI commands once
you install backlog MD obviously to
create task to list tasks to edit the
tasks and at the very beginning agents
would actually use this workflow. Now I
switched to MCP and I will tell you uh
later about it but it's it was already
way more effective this way.
So the
end result is something that looks
exactly like this. This is uh uh one of
the tasks of backlog MD for
fixing some some MCP issues I had. So uh
we have a front matter section with
metadata. This is a um some some
standard uh markdown section where you
can define uh metadata using lamb yam uh
language.
Then we have the task description,
the acceptance criterias
and uh the implementation plan. So this
would be written before working on the
task and the implementation notes after
the task is completed uh in case we want
to see what happened in that task.
And this is the first review step. This
is important that at this point when you
ask agent to create a task from your
description from your idea
you have the first review step and later
in the workshop uh I will put some
emphasis with with everyone of you that
you really check uh carefully what the
agent thinks it has to implement from
from your request.
So agents can easily use backlog MD or
either using CLI or MCP. So I started
with uh agents using the CLI and this
works with basically every agent. But
the newer ones that have MCP support,
they have more enhanced uh commands
because with MCP you can uh define the
schema of of the commands and the agent
knows what is available and what is not
available, what is uh required field,
what is an optional field and so on. And
uh this was just an example uh this was
an example of with the uh CLI. So for
example
um here Claude uh I think so I ask him I
asked it to work on a task and he
immediately put the task in progress and
assign it to itself using the CLI
commands. This is something that you
yourself can do. So it's not like you
need to use AI agents with backlog but
uh it's meant for being used with AI
agents that's uh makes everything much
simpler. So how the how do AI agents
know how to use backlog.
So when you uh later in the workshop you
will install backlog and the first thing
that you will uh run in your repository
is backlog init command. it the first
thing that it ask you apart from the
name is how do you want your AI agents
to connect with the tasks with backlog
MD and you can choose the MCP or the CLI
or you can skip but uh like that's not
how you would use it with AI agents and
via MCP it will install the instructions
for the AI agents um to to know how to
use backlog and when to use certain tool
certain features of backlog. So this
init command also with uh push some uh
instructions to your agent
to read the the backlog workflow. So
it's a very small uh instruction that it
will be pushed your on your agents MD or
cloud MD that says hey cloud MD this is
a project that is managed by uh backlog
MD for any task related request the user
gives to you please uh read this back uh
backlog overview. So this is uh much
better than using the CLI integration
because the agent can choose to read
this information depending on the task
that you ask because if you just ask hey
can you add this line of code to this
file you don't need to create a task for
it uh the tasks are only for bigger more
complex features so cloud would normally
see say okay do I need to create a task
no then I just do it. So if it it needs
to create a task then it will go read
this uh workflow process. Obviously this
going to consume some context window but
then uh it will know how to use backlog
and I have also some nested resources
also for context optimization because I
don't want cloud to know how to create
task if the task is already created then
I just need to work on it. So we have uh
three additional um uh instructions
basically that the agents can read
dynamically whenever they need to work
on any of these parts. So task creation,
execution and completion.
So the agents uh so this is the only the
information how to use a backlog but
like exactly how to run commands in in
in backlog. So I'm using MCP tools for
this and uh agents have search task,
view task details, create tasks or
update tasks tools. Uh the CLI has also
a lot more commands. That's why uh it
started to be problematic to use the CLI
uh instructions for the agents because
as you can see here there
quite a lot of commands. So a lot of
like variations of the same command and
AI agents would have hard time to keep
all of this information in in their
context. So the more instructions they
have to work with the less they are
effective and this this is the reason
why using the CLI integration is not as
good as the MCP because I only give the
instructions of what they really need to
use.
Yeah. So it has a terminal user
interface. So uh we will see very later
like uh have you ever seen a canon board
in your terminal? So I I didn't so I had
to I wanted to build it. So that's how
it looks a bit blurry but later I will
uh actually show it how it looks. Uh
actually let me do it now. So this is uh
live. So have you seen a terminal cand
board in a slide deck actually working?
So this is how it looks. Um,
wait a second. I need to go to this
screen.
Yeah. So, it's uh it's live. Uh, this is
how uh this is like connected to the
backlog project. So, those are all tasks
from from backlog
uh usual comban uh columns. You can add
more columns if you have a different
process. But it's very simple. It just
works. And you can also like see the
details of the task. So yeah,
acceptance criteria. So let's see one
task that is finished. Wait,
like here you can see uh mailmade
support for the web UI. I didn't uh get
to that point yet, but a spoiler. There
is also a web interface for backlog. And
you can see acceptance criteria are done
and the implementation notes hopefully
yeah what has been done in this task.
So let me
all right
so yeah
there is
web interface like I said earlier so
uh it's basically u sort of a J ripoff
but like coded by me um it's running
locally so what you have to do is just
run backlog browser and it's going to
spin off a offline uh server that where
you can manage your task. You can create
task and everything happens on your uh
computer. There is no need for internet
uh login
um anything like this. There's no
database. When you edit or create a new
task, it's going to actually save it on
your file system as markdown file. So
it's uh it's very very simple. And
there's a dark mode obviously.
So uh yeah uh backlog is free is uh MIT
licensed uh works offline. So obviously
if you want to use it with an agent you
need to be online. But if you want to
create 50 tasks ahead of time you can
just do it either from the CLI or from
the web interface
uh works on any platforms.
And
this is a question that I get often.
What if I'm working with other people on
the same project? Will they see my task?
Will they uh see what I'm doing? So the
answer is yes. But you have to push your
stuff. So obviously I cannot see changes
that you did in your local git repo
unless you push them. And uh backlog
uses a lot of git commands under the
hood to keep tasks in sync. So let's let
me give you two examples. I create a new
task and this is task ID 320.
And when I push this, other people will
see it in their own backlog running on
on the same repo as long as it's they
are connected to the same origin. And uh
if I put a task in progress on on one of
my branches, doesn't matter as long as
it's pushed, anyone from uh from their
uh repo from the other computer will see
the status changed. Maybe it's in
progress. It's uses like a lot of like
git uh fetch git commands uh magic under
the hood but it usually works.
So uh the ex the the reason why I say it
works is because backlog MD has been
written like from ground with backlog
MD. uh apart from the very three tasks
at the third task I was already having a
sort of recursive way to add new tasks
and have AI agents working on
implementing these tasks. And basically
it evolved like this and uh it was also
a challenge for me to not write any code
manually. So even if I know what is the
solution for this problem, I still asked
AI to fix it and to try to understand
because it for me backlog MD was more
like a learning process.
The only uh code like files that I wrote
manually are the instructions. So, how
to use backlog and when to use certain
commands.
And yeah, we got to almost 4,000 stars
uh by now. I'm not sure if we're there
yet, but we're very close. Uh it was
featured on the first page of Hacker
News some time ago.
And on Reddit the post about using
backlog MD was very very popular.
So but what I explained to you what is
backlog MD and I will explain what is
not backlog MD because I'm already
anticipating some of your questions.
So it's not a command uh center for
creating and delegating tasks to agents.
You can do that but not directly from
backlog MD. So you create your task and
then you go to codex you go to cloud and
say hey work on that task. So it's not
something like conductor or vibe can
there are like other projects that I
recommend if you want to have like a
command center where you create tasks
and they say like implement it.
Uh it's it's backlog MD it's meant to be
more like a tool that everyone uses and
uh should be as simple as possible.
is not hosted. So there's no backlog MD
resource to my git repo, but that's it.
You have to run install it on your
computer. You have to run it locally
either with the web interface or with
the CLI. But um some some uh people
asked me recently, hey, can you expose
your backlog to the internet? I'm like,
you don't want to do that because then
you have like hundreds of millions of
security issues, authentication,
permissions, and it's going to be hell.
uh you already have git in place. So I
assume everyone that has access to the
git repo has the correct permissions to
push things and this is how backlog MD
works. If you can push a change then it
means you have the correct permissions
on this repo. What it what is not there
yet is okay I I need my PM project
manager to look at the tasks. They will
have to have access to the repo. So
backlog MD is not good for kind that
kind of uh workflows.
It runs in your repo and it really uses
the git commands to sync between uh
tasks between multiple branches. It
cannot work with multiple repos.
And I started working on uh adding
documents and decisions features. So not
just tasks but imagine like long lived
specs about how to do testing, how to
um I don't know like what is the
language patterns that we're using TDD,
BDD, whatever. You don't want to put
them in a single task. You want to put
them in some long live documents. So I
started working on them. They're quite
alpha and I I want to work on them in
the next weeks. The goal would be to be
able to reference this local uh
documentation from your code files. So
let's say you have a function that does
something complex and it's connected
with some other parts of your repo. You
can link to the backlog MD document file
that says okay this is how we doing
things in this way. So that's that's
going to be uh next also I get a lot of
requests can I integrate this with gina
GitHub issues? No. So it's not meant for
that and I think if I start working on
that I will have to quit my current job
to be able to support all of these
features. So because backlog MD is just
uh my side project to learn more about
AI I cannot support all of these
features
but those tools themselves are slowly uh
adding MCP server or AI based tools. So
you could use them directly. You don't
need to use backlog MD for this. I think
like overall I uh the feeling I I want
to give you for backlog MD is that is
nice to use it for side projects where
you want to keep structure of of a
bigger project that you want to build
but you don't want to set up linear GR
and then have the AI agent connect to an
online linear something like this. You
want to have the quickest simplest
solution possible in your report. This
this is uh what is this backlog for
and as I said earlier this is my side
project so I cannot provide production
grade support like I'm doing for uh my
current job.
So
uh we're almost done with the um the
introduction then we will go to the
workshop. So first I I want to give you
a bit more information about the
specdriven AI development
and we will try to use this flow during
the workshop. So what is the specdriven
AI development is first you start with
knowing what what to build like this
seems obvious but I know a lot of
developers that try to understand what
they want to build before even like
starting prompting the AI and this with
AI doesn't work. it doesn't work very
well with humans writing code. It's it's
really bad for AI. So you for if you
don't know what you want to build, maybe
you can do iterations with AI, that's
fine and it's going to give you the
information you need. But for the
specdriven development, you want to have
all the information ahead of time. So
you can have product product requirement
document or other uh tools.
Then uh you would like to like structure
like create the structure for for this
bigger feature that you have in mind
into smaller tasks. Uh and we will do
this later with backlog MD.
And when you start working on a single
task, you would like to have the AI
agent create a plan for how to implement
this.
And my suggestion would be to only work
on one single task at a time just to not
fill the context window too much. Ask
the AI agent to understand your repo,
understand the task and the acceptance
criteria and then create an
implementation plan for how to actually
solve this. And then you actually review
this and this is the last step before uh
AI writes code. So this is the the right
moment to to do the final review uh
before writing the code. And then the
last part if everything went right until
here in my experience the code uh is is
always uh decent like it's it's not what
you didn't expect because in the
implementation plan you will see that
there are some some issues. So uh this
part is usually the simplest but what
what is important for the
code implementation is that if you see
there are some issues during the
implementation of the task you can try
to improve the agent instructions or the
task specifications themselves and
restart from scratch and not have the
same issues again and then iterate with
the next task. So uh a recap of of the
flow that we're going to do today. So
you start with an idea and you want you
will create the product requirement
document. We can look into some
structures that you can use but it's
very simple.
Um you will have this structure of why
what and uh that's why and the what is
in the in the requirements and then the
agent will come up with the how
and then you will tell agent hey
creates. So this is um this is the what
we're going to do in the workshop
actually. So the first you're going to
start with the PRDM MD. This is not
backlog MD at all. This is just um the
simplest way to to have a structured
output that the agent will work and then
we'll split into smaller task with
backlog MD. Uh later now backlog MD will
come into uh place and then you will
split it into smaller tasks.
You will review them and adjust and
basically it's going to work more or
less like this. So you ask the agent to
create task, the agent will create it
using the MCP or the CLI
and um nice to have if you're using an
AI agent if it can uh connect to the
internet and research for the less
latest best practices because a lot of
times uh what the data that they have
been trained on is not up to date. So if
you want to use the latest tailwind or
the latest library um they can actually
go on the internet and search for the
latest uh information.
Then you basically check in a task. You
will create the implementation plan. The
AI agent will create it for you. You
will just verify and it will be stored
uh in the backlog MD task itself.
Uh also another reason why you should
not have uh too many tasks running in
parallel having the implementation plans
for all of them at once is because maybe
you you will have a feature that has I
don't know 10 tasks and by the time you
get to the 10th task all of the
information of the how of the previous
task is going to be obsolete because
they might change uh while you're
working. So it's important to create the
implementation plan right before the
agent uh implements the task.
Then review and adjust and then um go to
the execution.
So um the execution is basically just
hey um clude please work on task number
one from backlog MD and claude would
know how to read it and how to work on
it.
And
let me have the workflow here.
This is how it uh how the whole flow
works. So you work on task one two
three. The agent reads the task from the
markdown file uh via backlog MD the CLI
or MCP and then starts writing your code
and then repeat the loop go on with the
next task.
So final conclusions, you need to know
what you want to build. Uh it's going to
be very hard to verify what the agents
build if you don't know uh what you want
to achieve either as a project manager,
either as a developer. It's similar.
Um you also need to know how to ensure
quality. So I think this flow works very
well for a intermediate senior developer
because only then you can actually tell
if the agents did a did a good job
and don't expect 100% quality. Uh
backlog MD had a lot of bugs at the very
beginning that I uh I slowly fixed over
time but AI agents are not perfect right
now and I think it's just good to accept
good enough result and move on.
Uh if something is completely
wrong or poorly implemented, you can
always go back to the task, change the
requirements and start over again.
And testing and linting and formatting
is also very important or like
pre-commit hooks. Uh those things are
working very well with AI agents.
Uh right now the human input is uh very
very important. So you need to do the
review at the end. Uh but you also need
to do the the other three reviews. So
after the task is created and the
acceptance criteria,
after the implementation plan and at the
end the code review
and especially for UI, it's very hard to
for the AI agent to test themsel the
result of their work. So probably some
of you use Chrome DevTools MCP. How
many? Few. Yeah. So with Chrome Web
Tools U MCP, you can actually have the
agent spin up Chrome instance and test
the the UI, but it's not perfect. And
also like not everything has a web
interface. Some some things have a
native a native interface. So it will
not work.
So uh I I will repeat this multiple
times. So one task per context window. I
learned it the hard way. So, Lada also
uh explained this very well. So, it's
not just important that you have context
window to work with, but also the the
quality of the work of AI agent degrades
a lot midway. So, um you always want to
have as as little context window used as
possible. And if you start if you think
that okay, I finished the task and I
still have 50% context window left. I
can start a second task in the same
session. Don't do this because the the
chances that the second task will be
done very very poorly are very high.
Also, uh we talked earlier about
compaction actually OpenAI and Antropic
multiple times on X and even on their
documentation they say they recommend to
not use compaction
even though they implement the feature
themselves. So they they have it but
they say don't use it.
Um
so with backlog MD you can have easily
this this process where you have one
task one context window and because it's
very important to split task correctly.
This is also like a project management
ability that developers would have to
have.
So um like I said you need to know how
to split a big project or a big feature
into into smaller task. This is a human
ability. This is not this is something
that AI can help. But this is something
that you yourself have to review and
verify that it's done correctly.
And once you have problems, solve it
once and solve it forever by changing
the agent instructions. So agent MD or
cloud MD.
This is very important because sometimes
uh same agents would repeat the same
problems. they would fall into the same
issues like maybe not writing the test
correctly or maybe cloud deleting the
test uh to make them pass. This happened
to me many times. So you just have to
update this uh agent instructions and
just tell them hey don't delete tests
make them pass at whatever cost
and this will uh drastically improve um
uh your workflow
and
um yeah so I started from just prompting
and I ended up here. I think I'm the
there are still uh room for improvement,
but it's already like good enough for me
to uh let AI agents code and finish
features in backlog MD and then I just
review the code at the end. So I think
it might also help you.
Um that's it for the first part. So
thank you. Now we have some questions
maybe um this is the link for the slides
and we will have also like five minutes
break so that you can go to the bathroom
take some water some uh prepare your
laptop for the workshop.
So question
yes uh do we have the microphone? Yeah.
>> Yeah. I have a question here. Um I see
the backlog and the um and I don't know
if that was your intention where you
built it, but it looks really focused um
for developers and I was wondering if
there is a mode or if you thought about
like making it nicer for people that
don't necessarily have a technical
background on it. Um actually so uh yeah
that's actually something that my
friends that are not developers ask me
like hey can can you help me use backlog
MD for uh uh planning marketing uh
campaigns.
This is a very common use case where
people try to use backlog MD for. So you
can split uh you can initialize backlog
in your repo. So you need to know what
is a repository. You need to know git uh
uh in it or like this kind of stuff. But
then afterwards you can use the web
interface for this. But to be honest I'm
not sure if this is
much better better than I don't know
Trello or Aana or like because it's more
port. So for example Azana is more
portable. You can have it on your phone
or you can have it on your computer.
Here with git you would have to have a
git client. So you would have to run
backlog and your git client on on each
of your devices and for example from
your phone you will not be able to see
your tasks. So I I think to get to that
point I will have to work a lot and
implement probably like the SAS version
of backlog MD and this not it's not in
my plans here.
Uh yes,
>> you
uh super exciting talk. Sounds like
we're on the same page in a lot of ways.
Um one thing that uh at least on Curo,
we spend a lot of time thinking about is
when we go for kind of spec driven dev,
we go from we do the same thing you do
effectively, uh requirements into
design, implementation, and then
execution. Um we've actually gotten a
lot of feedback from people that they
want to flip the way they're thinking
about like they want to think in code
first maybe for things like refactor
tasks etc where the requirement is not
necessarily clear up front. Have you
done any experimentation with sort of
retroactively pulling your task
requirements out of [snorts] maybe a
code diff or a patch or something like
that? Um
so kind of so what I realized recently I
mean so uh all of these agents use LLM
based models under the hood. LLM based
models are like autocomplete on
steroids. They just given your prompt
try to write the code from it. And the
the the
solution to this is to make them go at
at the very end start from the end and
then go backwards. So you by by doing
this thing with the code that you said
it's sort of like good showing them the
end result like where you want to like
the end state and try to ask them hey
how can I get from this code to that
state so that's more or less similar to
what you are saying but yeah once you
have some code snippet that you you tell
them like yeah they it's much more
efficient for them to create like the
plan how to get to that state uh but I
didn't like concretely try to hey give
this this is the code that I would like
to have at the end can we can we build
specs from it
>> yeah
any other questions
okay no then so it's uh 150 let's have
where is Simon
maybe 10 minutes break until two
Yeah. Uh so let's meet again at 2 and
then we start with the workshop. So are
you ready? Are you refreshed? Do you
have the laptop and the idea ready?
So how it's going to how the workshop uh
is going to work? So let me
uh go to the slide here. So we're going
to uh experiment with the flow that I
showed you earlier. So first of all,
we're going to make sure that everyone
has backlog installed and backlog in it
in the uh git repo. If you have any
issues, I will go around the uh desks
and help you. Then uh you're going to
create the tasks and try to say
something to clude. Hey Clude, please
implement this huge prompt that you have
in mind uh with backlog MD and split it
in in tasks and I will assist you if you
have any issues
and then once you have the tasks then
you will check in as one task at the
time and you will ask claude to create
an implementation plan and if it matches
your expectation then you ask him ask it
to actually work on the on the code and
then you will do the code review. So
let's start with the first. So let's uh
please install backlog uh go to
backlog.mmd on your browser. It's a
molddova domain. So it will work. Um
there you have the instructions how to
install it.
Uh yeah let's let's have this step first
and then once everyone is more or less
ready then you can proceed autonomously
and if you need me for anything just
raise your hand and I will try to go
around and help you if you get stuck.
Okay good.
luck. So I got asked um once you install
and run back login it what's next? So um
what's next is you open your AI agent in
the same repo and then uh given that you
doing the backlog in it you selected
correctly which agent you're uh going to
use the agent should know that backlog
exists and how to use it. So at this
point so basically just open Gemini
Codeex code
or or anything in the same folder where
you run backlog in it and then the agent
should pick it up correctly. Um and then
you just give the to the agent the idea
that you want to build and ask to split
it in subtasks. So another question I
got is do I have to start with a plan MD
file necessarily? Uh no this is just so
that you don't uh like write a huge huge
text directly in cloud or your AI agent
because if you do like if you press the
wrong button and if you submit it by
mistake that's uh going to be an issue.
So that's why I uh suggested to start
with a plan domarkdown or whatever file
so that you can like type in it and then
like revi uh do some revisions before
you copy the whole uh plan inside the
cloud instance. So I realized one of the
third part is a bit misleading it. Uh so
what you should not understand from this
create the tasks and then create the
implementation plan for all of the tasks
immediately afterwards.
um
you should only like start working on a
single task and uh have the agent create
the implementation plan for that task
not for all of them because what uh I
just see happening is that if you create
implementation plan for all of the tasks
you might change a lot the the
infrastructure of the previous tasks and
then the implementmentation plan is
obsolete. So just do all of the tasks at
the beginning that's fine but then when
you start working on a single task do
the implementation plan for that task
only. So um I just got a crazy good idea
about how to evolve um backlog MD and
let me show you something that I didn't
show before that actually works uh with
backlog MD. So let's let's vibe code it.
So
have you ever used uh Codex web
like Codex but like the managed by them
and hosted by them?
Not not many some. Okay. So
uh backlog also works with codecs. So
because of the there's no MCP
integration yet here but there is the
CLI it can just like install backlog MD
and run it. So this uh allows you to do
something like uh just select here the
correct repo.
Okay. And select the branch and just say
what task you want to build. So here the
request was um to add callbacks to uh
when I move a task into in progress or
into done. So trigger some other
additional um tools that that I have on
my computer. So let me write it here and
then I will have Codex creating the
task. Maybe I should split it into
creating the task first, checking if
it's correct, then I will ask it to
implement it.
Love is
going.
Don't look away.
Don't look.
Take your love.
around
just a
>> Yeah. So this is just another way you
can use backlog MD. Actually uh what I
do a lot of times I I get an idea. So uh
for me walking my dog is like the moment
where I get the best ideas. So when I'm
walking my dog obviously I don't have my
laptop with me and I just uh take Chad
Guptity app that also has the Codex web
uh hosted Codex version on it and then I
just give the idea and then when I
finish the the walk with my dog I get
back I get the PR with the the task
created so then I can actually work on
it. This is also like one side effects
of having backlog using a CLI to uh to
run to create tasks.
It's going to take some time. Codex web
uh needs to spin up a new environment
and we might not be able to see the
results. But when Codex finishes, it uh
it asks you to create a PR against your
repo. So I think here it's already it's
almost done. It was very fast this time
but usually it takes some time and um
yeah then you have a PR that you can
start working with it.
Happy
birthday.
Hey,
hey, hey.
Okay. So task is created. So
uh let me do the next step. So let's let
me review it one more time. So allow
task to define shell command callbacks
in front matter that run automatically
when task status changes. Commands
should execute when status updates are
triggered through backlog MD workflows
and should be configurable as bash
commands. Task from meta supports. Yeah,
looks okay. I mean normally you would
reverify but we're uh I'm just uh
demonstrating the feature. So create PR
and now I can review one more time. But
if I merge this, this will be part of
the tasks I have in my repo. So I can
just uh login on my laptop and say cloud
please implement task 318.
Uh yeah this created the file in the
backlog tasks. Yeah it used backlog
itself. So you can see uh it used
correctly the CLI uh because you have
this markers for the sections because
when you don't see these markers
sometimes uh AI hallucinates to try to
create tasks because backlog MD is is
also like a way to just store all of
your backlog in a markdown file. Uh so
some agents when they don't read the
instructions they will hallucinate this
part but when you see the correct
markers it means that it went through
backlog MD CLI. Uh actually I got a
question a bit earlier like uh why not
using cloud web tasks or Google jewels.
Uh none of the two works as good as
codex because in codex web you can
configure your your container however
you want. So you can say okay I'm going
to install backlog MD as the first thing
that when the container spins up. You
can't do as much in Google jewels and uh
cloud web tasks. If you manage to do it
please let me know because I would
really like to use those other tools but
Codex is already good enough for just
creating a task on the fly.
>> Say it again.
Uh so the question is can you use both
the CLI integration and the MCP
integration? I would not recommend that
uh for the following reason. The CLI
instructions uh I consider them legacy.
They are huge line huge file with all of
the instructions all of the commands
that are available and they pollute the
context a lot. The MCP is it's the new
approach and uh the agent reads the
instructions based on what it has to do.
If you use both you'll get the CLI uh
context pollution and the benefits of
MCP I would not use them at the same
time. In fact, uh recently when you uh I
changed it that if you if backlog MD
doing during backlog in it detects the
CLI instructions, it will override them
with the MCP instructions which are much
smaller because yeah, otherwise you take
10% of your context window just with the
CLI instructions.
uh one thing. So, I noticed that uh some
of you uh put uh start my start the repo
and I successfully passed 4,000 GitHub
stars. So, thank you very much.
[applause]
I I didn't plan it like I didn't like
paid some people to start right before
4,000, but it's it's nice that it
happened like right during the workshop.
Also,
is anyone using uh Gemini 3 already?
One
because it came out during the previous
workshop. I installed it, but I didn't
manage to use it. So, I'm cur I'm going
to come to you and see uh how good it is
with backlog.
So, we're getting close to the end.
Let's have like few more like 10 more
minutes of uh like playing around. then
you can experiment with backlog MD like
uh afterwards this evening next weeks.
Uh just a note tomorrow I'm giving a
talk about backlog MD. It's a 20 minutes
version of what we did today without the
workshop and without uh many of the
things. Um if you want to join please do
you you're welcome to come but it's
going to be like a light version of what
we had today. So if you want to have a
recap of what what we uh did today, you
can also join to the talk tomorrow. But
just know that it's not something new or
different that what we did today.
So I had the quark code here. Uh
unfortunately Cloudflare broke today and
my Raspberry Pi didn't recover
automatically. It's not a multi-tenant
super fancy setup. is just a Raspberry
Pi with a web server and I have the
slides also deployed there and it needs
someone to actually kick it manually to
make it work. So this evening I'm going
to contact uh I'm going to have the the
Raspberry Pi getting rebooted and
hopefully tomorrow you will find this uh
talk on the my my website here. So this
will if you can bookmark or like save it
somehow uh tomorrow should be working
fine.
All right, time's up. Thank you everyone
for joining my workshop. I hope you had
fun with Backlog MD. Um, you can still
uh find me around uh today and tomorrow.
If you have questions, uh, please let me
know. And thanks again for coming.
[music]